Guide to the Oliver Allen Papers on the Historic Preservation of Tribeca 1985-2002 (bulk 1985-1994) MS 3058
New-York Historical Society
Oliver Allen papers on the historic preservation of Tribeca
1985-2002 (bulk 1985-1994)
New-York Historical Society
Allen, Oliver E., 1922-2017
MS 3058
.63 Linear Feet in 2 document boxes
The Oliver Allen papers on the historic preservation of Tribeca document the efforts and achievements to approve this neighborhood in lower Manhattan as a designated historic district by New York City. Oliver Allen was the Vice Chair of the Committee for the Washington Market Historic District, which was affiliated with the Tribeca Community Association. These groups were primarily responsible for advocating Tribeca as a worthy historic preservation district and obtaining the designation from City Council.
Arrangement
The original order and titles of folders as they were received by N-YHS were retained for this collection. The arrangement is topical and chronological within like topics.
Biographical / Historical
Oliver E. Allen (1922-2017) played a fundamental role in the designation of Tribeca as a recognized historic district by the Landmarks Preservation Commission and the New York City Council. Professionally, he was a writer and editor for Life magazine and later an editor at Time-Life Books. He wrote over a dozen books and published well over one hundred articles. In 1989 he contributed to the book "The Texture of Tribeca" by Andrew Dolkart, which was used to promote the mission of the Tribeca Community Association. As a longtime resident of Tribeca he volunteered his time to historic preservation efforts in the area. He was the Vice Chair of the Committee for the Washington Market Historic District and one of the founders of Friends of Duane Park. He was a regular contributor to The Tribeca Trib, a publication covering Lower Manhattan, writing articles about the history of Tribeca. He resided at 42 Hudson Street, New York, in a loft overlooking Duane Park with his wife Deborah (d. 2014). Together they had four children, five grandchildren, and two great-grandchildren. An interview with Oliver Allen was conducted by The New York Preservation Archive Project in 2010 and can be found here: NYPAP Oliver Allen Oral History
Tribeca is an abbreviation for the "triangle below canal." Before adopting the name Tribeca in the 1970s, the area was known as Washington Square Market. This former name was chosen for the committee of which Oliver Allen was vice chair and it is found on the folders in this collection. Tribeca runs from Canal Street on the North, Broadway on the East, Vesey Street on the South, and West Street on the West. The area was split into four separate historic districts being: Tribeca North, East, South and West. Tribeca West, which covers about 17 blocks, was the first to be designated and approved as a historic district in 1991. The other three districts, North (about 10 blocks), East (about 10 blocks), and South (5 blocks), were designated as historic districts by the Landmarks Preservation Commission in 1992 and approved by City Council on April 1, 1993. The Tribeca South Extension was designated as a historic district in 2002, though that event is not covered in this collection. This Landmarks Preservation Commission map shows the Tribeca historic districts and full designation reports may be read.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift from Oliver Allen, 2015.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of Oliver Allen's papers during the period from the mid-1980s to mid-1990s that the Committee for the Washington Market Historic District and the Tribeca Community Association were advocating for the designation of Tribeca as a historic preservation district. The records consist of meeting notes, public hearing announcements, correspondence, photographs taken by Allen, Landmarks Preservation Commission memorandum, clippings, fliers, pamphlets, statements, task lists, Tribeca area maps, and other documents related to the topic of historic preservation in Tribeca. Important activists such as Carole De Saram, president of the Tribeca Community Association, and Hal Bromm, gallery owner and chair of The Committee for the Washington Market Historic District show up numerous times within these papers. The documents show interactions with many agencies including the Tribeca Community Association (TCA), the Landmarks Preservation Commission (LPC), the Historic Districts Council (HDC), the City Planning Commission (CPC), and the New York City Council (NYCC).
TriBeCa (New York, N.Y.); TriBeCa (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Historic preservation -- New York (State) -- New York; Historic districts -- New York (State) -- New York.; Bromm, Hal; De Saram, Carole
- Washington Market Historic District, 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Contains black and white photographs of Tribeca buildings and architecture
- Washington Market Historic District, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Washington Market Historic District, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Washington Market Historic District, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Contains a copy of the statement signed by actor Robert DeNiro presented to the Landmarks Preservation Commission in 1989
- Washington Market Historic District, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Historic District: Final Phase, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Historic District: Final Phase, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Contains 3 copies of "The Epic of Tribeca", written by Oliver Allen, dated May 24, 1993. 5 page rhyming poem describing the efforts of Tribeca community members
- Tribeca Historic District - Maps and Artwork, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Tribeca Historic District - Planning Group, circa 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Tribeca - Miscellaneous file, circa 1987-2002 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Contains typescript, "A History of The Duane Park Building"
- Tribeca Historic District - Auction, Other Benefits, circa 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Landmarks - General, 1986-1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Tribeca Historic District - Book Sales, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)